{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "In this city, a dramatization of the novel The Two Captains was broken up at the start of a terrorist attack. Civilian casualties in this city escalated after troops refused to tell doctors what type of chemical weapon they had used, leading to the death of 130 hostages. The Spetsnaz special forces indiscriminately used poison gas to end a hostage crisis in, for ten points, what city where Chechen terrorists occupied the Dubrovka Theater in 2002?",
      "answer": "Moscow"
    },
    {
      "question": "This general died in a battle in which the Arcadian League splintered. This man’s last words were legendarily “I have lived long enough; for I die unconquered,” and he noted that he left behind an “immortal” daughter: a battle where he defeated Cleombrotus, Leuctra. This man’s death at the Battle of Mantinea essentially ensured that Philip II of Macedon would be able to conquer Greece. The Sacred Band fought for, for ten points, what massively successful Theban general?",
      "answer": "Epaminondas"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man was forced to step down after the Rua Tonelero incident, in which an assassination attempt was launched on rival Carlos Lacerda. The Integralists were suppressed by this man after they advocated for fascism. This man declared he would “leave life to enter history” before shooting himself with a pistol. During his tenure, he established Petrobras and administered the South American Estado Novo period. For ten points, name this president of Brazil in the 1940s.",
      "answer": "Getulio Vargas"
    },
    {
      "question": "This owner of the Poplar Hall plantation wrote that the “difficulty of establishing particular manufactures [...] is almost insuperable” in the second entry of a series that this man published under the name “A Farmer.” This man’s most famous work was addressed to a king who refused to read it, instead proclaiming that the colonists had “proceeded to open and avowed rebellion.” For ten points, name this “Penman of the Revolution,” a founding father from Pennsylvania who drafted the Olive Branch Petition.",
      "answer": "John Dickinson"
    },
    {
      "question": "In a work by this man, the line “either I’m nobody, or I’m a nation” is spoken by Shabine, who later comments on the Middle Passage. This man lamented about the bad deeds of “Hawkins, Walter Raleigh, [and] Drake” in another work, which notes that the “smell of dead limes” signifies the “leprosy of empire.” This poet described the sinking of the Marlborough in a work in which Achille loves Major Dennis Plunkett’s servant, Helen. For ten points, name this Saint Lucian poet who wrote the Iliad-inspired “Omeros.”",
      "answer": "Derek Walcott"
    },
    {
      "question": "Fighting for this city included the second battle of the Odon and Verrieres Ridge. Defenses in this city were compromised after nearby Saint Lo was captured, and this city was finally abandoned after Allied troops launched Operations Cobra and Spring. Many retreating German troops were trapped in the Falaise Pocket after this city fell, paving the way for a push into central France. For ten points, name this city in Normandy that was contested for three months following D-Day.",
      "answer": "Caen"
    },
    {
      "question": "After the president of a neighboring country, Sylvanus Olympio, was assassinated, a ruler of this country named Maurice Yameogo began removing government ministers. A ruler of this country fought the Agacher Strip war with its northern neighbor; that man was known as “the Che Guevara of Africa,” Thomas Sankara. A 2014 uprising in this country ousted Blaise Compaor´e, who fled to the Ivory Coast. For ten points, name this landlocked African country where Roch Kabor´e leads from Ouagadougou.",
      "answer": "Burkina Faso"
    },
    {
      "question": "One of these events sparked unrest in Chicago that became the Battle of the Viaduct on Halsted Street. One of these events which began in Martinsburg, Virginia led to the Shamokin Uprising and many other smaller actions. One of these events in 1922 occurred in response to wage cuts that notably did not affect the “Big Four” unions in its industry. A “Great” one of these events in 1877 lasted for 45 days before being put down by federal troops across the country; that event targeted the B&O. For ten points, name this type of labor action, common in late 19th century America as transportation barons exploited workers.",
      "answer": "railroad strikes"
    },
    {
      "question": "This philosopher originated the image of a “tree falling in a forest” with nobody around to hear it as part of an argument that God must exist to percieve the whole universe at all times. That image, which later reappeared in a limerick, comes from this thinker’s Treatise Concerning the Principles of Human Knowledge. This thinker later wrote that “to be is to be perceived” in Three Dialogues Between Hylas and Philonous. For ten points, name this “immaterialist” Anglo-Irish philosopher who lends his name to a university city in California.",
      "answer": "Bishop George Berkeley , but be lenient"
    },
    {
      "question": "This doctrine was used in conjunction with the concept of “bad tendency” in the conviction of a man who published a “Left Wing Manifesto.” Since Brandenburg v. Ohio, this doctrine has been replaced by the idea of “imminent lawless action.” This doctrine was introduced in an opinion that described the evils of “falsely shouting fire in a theatre.” Schenck v. U.S. originated, for ten points, what four-word doctrine by which justice Oliver Wendell Holmes described situations in which free speech was not protected by the Constitution?",
      "answer": "clear and present danger"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A song about this structure included a chorus with the lines “And you’ll always know your neighbor / And you’ll always know your pal” and was written by Thomas Allen. Canvass White developed a new type of cement while working on this structure. Cities like May’s Point and Lockport were along this structure, whose construction was opposed by the Bucktails. This structure, which opened in 1825, passed through the Mohawk Valley. DeWitt Clinton commissioned, for ten points, what canal running from Buffalo to Albany?",
        "answer": "Erie Canal"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "After Benjamin Wright served as chief engineer of the Erie Canal, he worked on this 14-mile-long canal that connects its namesake bay and river at the northern limit of the Delmarva Peninsula.",
        "answer": "Chesapeake & Delaware Canal"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Four canvases featuring depictions of this figure had bullets driven through them by Dorothy Podber. The last professional photograph of this figure features a kiss blown on a Santa Monica beach. Replica artist Elaine Sturtevant used an original still from the film Niagara for a depiction of this woman that was inspired by fifty silk-screen prints created by Andy Warhol. The first cover of Playboy magazine featured, for ten points, what actress, born as Norma Jeane Mortenson?",
        "answer": "Marilyn Monroe"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In addition to having bullets destroy his depictions of Marilyn Monroe, Andy Warhol was the target of an assassination attempt by Valerie Solanas, the only known member of what appropriately- named radical feminist organization?",
        "answer": "Society for Cutting Up Men or SCUM"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Prior to this event, Avner Less was placed in charge of interrogations. This event led to an execution that took place at Ramla. Robert Servatius led the defense in this trial, which led Hannah Arendt to coin the term “banality of evil” to describe the use of the “following orders” defense. This event was made possible by Mossad’s capture of its subject in Argentina. For ten points, name this 1962 trial of a Nazi leader in Israel.",
        "answer": "trial of Adolf Eichmann ”trial” not needed after it is mentioned"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Eichmann facilitated and attended this 1942 conference where Nazi leaders systematized the implementation of the Holocaust.",
        "answer": "Wannsee Conference"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this state, Rafael Moneo designed a major postmodern cathedral to avoid right angles. Philip Johnson designed this state’s huge all-glass Crystal Cathedral. This state was the center of Jim Jones’s religious movement before the foundation of Jonestown in Guyana. Aimee Semple McPherson founded the Foursquare Church in, for ten points, what US state where Spanish catholics established missions in cities like San Francisco and Los Angeles?",
        "answer": "California"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This charismatic Christian movement originated with the Azusa Street Revival in California.",
        "answer": [
          "Pentecostalism",
          "word forms"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One of the countries involved in this event sabotaged ICAO investigations into it. This event was triggered by the actions of Major General Genadi Osipovich, and came after an increased period of tension between two nations from the FleetEx naval exercise. Deviations in heading after leaving Anchorage caused the subject of this event to fly through restricted airspace over Kamchatka, leading to its crash near Sakhalin. For ten points, name this 1983 incident in which a Soviet Su-15 fighter attacked a civilian flight.",
        "answer": [
          "shooting down or equivalents of Korean Air Lines Flight 007",
          "shooting down of KAL 007"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Georgia congressman and former president of the John Birch Society was killed aboard Korean Air Lines Flight 007.",
        "answer": "Larry McDonald"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This composer depicted the 1994 Los Angeles earthquake in I Was Looking at the Ceiling and Then I Saw the Sky. An opera by this composer begins with the “Chorus of Exiled Palestinians” and the “Chorus of Exiled Jews” and centers on the hijacking of the cruise ship Achille Lauro. The ballet “The Red Detachment of Women” is featured in an opera by this composer that begins with the title character stepping of The Spirit of ‘76. For ten points, name this American minimalist composer of Nixon in China.",
        "answer": "John Coolidge Adams"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This 69-year-old Jewish-American man was murdered on the Achille Lauro in 1985 and is the subject of Adams’ aforementioned opera.",
        "answer": [
          "Leon Klinghoffer",
          "The Death of Klinghoffer"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1540, this man was made adelantado of the R´ıo de la Plata. This explorer’s family name was supposedly inspired by an object that an ancestor of this man used to mark a secret pass at the Battle of Las Navas de Tolosa. With his Moorish slave Estevanico, this man was one of four who survived the Narv´aez expedition; that expedition was chronicled by this man in La Relac´ıon, the first account of the Americas written by a European. For ten points, name the Spanish conquistador of the early sixteenth century who was shipwrecked in the Gulf of Mexico and wandered the American southwest.",
        "answer": "A´lvar Nu´n˜ez Cabeza de Vaca"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The four survivors of the Narv´aez expedition re-encountered Spanish traders in what is now this Mexican state, south of Sonora. During the Mexican-American War, the US occupied the city of Mazatlan in this state.",
        "answer": "Sinaloa"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Roanoke Colony",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Modern-day state where the Lost Colony of Roanoke was located in the Outer Banks.",
          "answer": "North Carolina"
        },
        {
          "question": "Explorer who owned the charter over Roanoke; unrelatedly, he was twice imprisoned in the Tower of London.",
          "answer": "Sir Walter Raleigh"
        },
        {
          "question": "Foreign fleet whose 1588 attack on England delayed a resupply fleet to Roanoke.",
          "answer": "Spanish Armada"
        },
        {
          "question": "First English colonist born in the New World, who was born at Roanoke.",
          "answer": "Virginia Dare"
        },
        {
          "question": "Privateer who took the original colonists back to England in 1586, less than a decade after circumnavigating the globe.",
          "answer": "Sir Francis Drake"
        },
        {
          "question": "Word carved into a fencepost, providing the only hint for where the Lost Colonists went.",
          "answer": "CROATOAN"
        },
        {
          "question": "Symbol consisting of four V-shaped arrows that was to be carved if the colonists encountered trouble; no such symbol was found.",
          "answer": "Maltese cross"
        },
        {
          "question": "Surname of Richard, who led the first fleet of colonists to Roanoke, and William, a British PM who led the “Ministry of All the Talents.”",
          "answer": [
            "Grenville",
            "Sir Richard Grenville",
            "William Grenville, Lord Grenville"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Eminent Victorians",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "“Lady of the Lamp” who was credited as the founder of modern nursing after her work in Crimea.",
          "answer": "Florence Nightingale"
        },
        {
          "question": "Rival of William Gladstone, a Jewish prime minister who signed the Royal Titles Act.",
          "answer": "Benjamin Disraeli"
        },
        {
          "question": "Unknown serial killer who murdered at least 5 people in Whitechapel in 1888.",
          "answer": "Jack the Ripper"
        },
        {
          "question": "Prime minister who repealed the Corn Laws to alleviate the Irish Potato Famine.",
          "answer": "Sir Robert Peel"
        },
        {
          "question": "Army officer who won the Battle of Omdurman and appears on posters that inspired “Uncle Sam” in the US.",
          "answer": [
            "Horatio Herbert Kitchener, 1st Earl Kitchener",
            "Lord Kitchener"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Prime minister who initiated the Arrow War and resolved the Don Pacifico affair in 1850.",
          "answer": [
            "Henry John Temple, Viscount Palmerston",
            "Lord Palmerston"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Prime Minister who led England into the Boer War in his third term and won the first “khaki” election.",
          "answer": [
            "Robert Gascoyne-Cecil, Marquess of Salisbury",
            "Lord Salisbury"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Member of the Bloomsbury Group who wrote a renowned series of biographies called Eminent Victorians in 1918.",
          "answer": "Lytton Strachey"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Hakka People",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Asian island with capital at Taipei where Hakka dialects are widely spoken.",
          "answer": "Taiwan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Largest river of Northern China, from whose basin the Hakka likely migrated south.",
          "answer": [
            "Yellow River",
            "Huang He"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Series of wars with Britain in the 19th century in which Hakka generals played a leading role in the Qing navy.",
          "answer": "Opium Wars"
        },
        {
          "question": "Custom the Hakka refused to take part in, in which a certain body part was crushed to assume a “lotus” shape.",
          "answer": [
            "footbinding",
            "word forms and equivalents"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Trek across China, conducted mostly by Hakka soldiers after Communist defeats in battle in 1934.",
          "answer": "Long March"
        },
        {
          "question": "City where Hakka soldiers fought a Japanese siege during the Defense of Sihang Warehouse.",
          "answer": "Shanghai"
        },
        {
          "question": "Leader of the Taiping Rebellion whose army was mostly made up of Hakka.",
          "answer": "Hong Xiuquan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Circular clan houses, often several stories high, in which Hakka people traditionally live.",
          "answer": "tulou"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) While serving in this country’s legislature, William Anderson secured a $500,000 loan from Britain. European traders labeled an area of what became this country as the Pepper Coast. Edward James Roye briefly served as this country’s leader, its first from the True (20 pts)",
        "Whig Party that dominated its politics for a century. Joseph Jenkins Roberts was the first president of this country, which declared its independence in (10 pts)",
        "1847 and was created with the help of Henry Clay and other members of the American Colonization Society. For ten points, name this country, the first independent republic in Africa, whose capital is Monrovia."
      ],
      "answer": "Liberia"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s wife suffered a miscarriage after she heard the radio report of this man’s death, helping lead to the journalistic practice of informing families before reporting the names of fatalities. This man died after chartering a (20 pts)",
        "flight from Mason City, Iowa to Moorhead, Minnesota whose other passengers included “The Big Bopper” and (10 pts)",
        "Ritchie Valens. This artist, famous for his horn-rimmed glasses, recorded with The Crickets. For ten points, name this singer of “That’ll Be The Day,” an early rock-and-roll star who was killed in a 1959 plane crash that became known as “The Day the Music Died.”"
      ],
      "answer": "Buddy Holly or Charles Hardin Holley"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One side in this battle was bolstered by the arrival of John George’s forces, though those Saxon troops were later routed. During this battle, Johan Baner’s cavalry routed the Black Cuirassiers, who weren’t given the proper authority to charge and attacked because of the (20 pts)",
        "myth that a Pappenheim would save Germany from an invading king. The losing side in this battle was forced to rehire Albrecht (10 pts)",
        "Wallenstein to cover for the wounded Count Tilly. For ten points, name this 1631 battle fought near Leipzig, a great victory for Gustavus Adolphus in the Thirty Years’ War."
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Breitenfeld"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Members of this tribe sacked the town of Linville during the Great Raid of 1840, which may have been in retaliation for an incident in which twelve of their leaders were killed during peace talks, the Council House Fight. The Kiowa and this tribe agreed to relocate to smaller reservations as part of the first (20 pts)",
        "Medicine Lodge Treaty. Buffalo Hump and Quanah Parker were prominent leaders of the tribe, which often clashed with (10 pts)",
        "Texans throughout the nineteenth century. For ten points, name this tribe sometimes called the “Lords of the Southern Plains.”"
      ],
      "answer": "Comanche"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Scholars argue that an Arabic expansion of Diophantus’ Arithmetica was actually written by this thinker, citing an idiosyncratic method for dividing in base 60. After strife between the prefect Orestes and the patriarch (20 pts)",
        "Cyril broke out, this thinker was labeled a heretic and murdered by a Christian mob in 415 AD in (10 pts)",
        "her hometown of Alexandria, making her a martyr for future philosophers. Ptolemy’s Almagest was edited by, for ten points, what Neoplatonist philosopher and mathematician?"
      ],
      "answer": "Hypatia of Alexandria"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Eight howitzers were left buried in what is now this state during a Civil War retreat led by Henry Hopkins Sibley a few weeks after the Battle of Glorieta Pass here. A pair of cities in Kansas and a city in this state name the ATSF Railway; the same city names a (20 pts)",
        "trail blazed by William Becknell that linked with El Camino Real. This state’s (10 pts)",
        "Alamogordo Bombing Range was used for the Trinity test in 1945. The easternmost land of the Gadsden Purchase is now the southernmost land of, for ten points, what state where the Roswell UFO crash supposedly happened to the southeast of Albuquerque?"
      ],
      "answer": "New Mexico"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This leader’s navy was damaged when John Vassall was blackmailed into being a Soviet spy. Though this politician began the Polaris nuclear project, he ended the National Service and joined the USSR and United States as the third major country to sign the Partial Test Ban Treaty. This man’s (20 pts)",
        "cabinet was rocked by the revelation that Christine Keeler had an affair with the Secretary of State for War, John Profumo. This Prime Minister’s (10 pts)",
        "sub-Saharan tour of Africa is credited with speeding up decolonization. For ten points, name this Conservative Prime Minister of the UK who gave the 1960 “Wind of Change” speech in South Africa."
      ],
      "answer": "Harold MacMillan"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Curly Harris attempted to mitigate the financial losses caused by this event by having three of his employees dress in street clothes and act as customers. David Richmond and Ezell Blair were among the participants in this event, who were attendees of an (20 pts)",
        "Agricultural and Technical State University. After buying toothpaste, the four initial members of this event unsuccessfully tried to order a (10 pts)",
        "cup of coffee as employees appealed to a “whites only” policy. For ten points, name this 1960 event in which African-American students occupied a Woolworth lunch counter in North Carolina."
      ],
      "answer": "1960 Greensboro sit-ins"
    }
  ]
}